בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Today's דף Daf is ל"ז. Lamed Zayin. We pick up on the
bottom of ל"ו עמוד ב' Lamed Vav Amud Bais and we are
dealing with the הלכה Halacha that bleeding is a result of birth
pains does not make a woman a זבה; Zavah; it could make
a woman a נדה Niddah but not a זבה. Zavah. And we
pick up, okay, two lines in the wide lines and we
had learned the דרשה Drasha from the פסוק Pasuk that it said
זוב דמה Zov Damah by the זבה, Zavah, her blood, and not
the blood that results from a fetus. So a woman who bleeds
cannot become a as a result of the birth pains, cannot be
a זבה. Zavah. So the גמרא Gemara says two lines down in
the wide lines, ל"ו עמוד ב', Lamed Vav Amud Bais, אי הכי
נדה נמי, I hachi niddah nami, by a נדה Niddah as well,
נימא nima זובה zovah because also by the נדה Niddah it says
the same פסוק, Pasuk, it says her flow. So let's say זובה
מחמת עצמה ולא מחמת ולד, Zovah machmas atzmah velo machmas vlad, that
it's only that a woman also can't be a נדה Niddah if
it's coming from the fetus. אתו אומר ולד או אינו אלא אונס
Atu omer vlad o eino ela oness and maybe we'll say the
same thing, maybe you want to say no, maybe if any external
cause. כשהוא אומר אשה כי תהיה זבה, Keshehu omer ishah ki tihiyeh
zavah, if a woman flows, זבה Zavah somehow when she flows it's
just generic, it's not necessarily her flow. הרי אונס אמור, Harei oness
amur, that includes even a case of an אונס, Oness, an external
stimulation. המה אני מקיים זובה Ha-ma ani mekayem zovah
but it still says her flow later. זובה מחמת עצמה ולא מחמת
ולד, Zovah machmas atzmah velo machmas vlad, but not her and is
it not based on the fetus?
So the exact same thing we say by a זבה, Zavah, say
it by a נדה. Niddah. A woman would not also be able
to be a נדה Niddah as a result of the fetus. אמר
ריש לקיש אמר קרא, Amar Reish Lakish amar kra,
the פסוק Pasuk says תשב. Tayshev. By the יולדת Yolledet it says
וששים יום וששת ימים תשב על דמי טהרה, Vesheshishim yom vesheishes yamim
tayshev al demay taharah,
so she shall sit, she shall, meaning she shall be in the
state of still being טמאה tmeiah but the blood itself is טהור.
tahor. So יש לך ישיבה אחרת שהיא כזו. Yesh lcha yeshiva acheres
shehi kezu. ואיזו זו קושי בימי זיבה. Ve-eizu? Zu koshi bimei zivah.
Now,
because it says by the case of the childbirth that she shall,
that there's a period of טהרה, taharah, so that teaches us that
there's another period of טהרה taharah and that other period of טהרה
taharah can be blood as a result of זיבה zivah blood as
a result of the fetus. Now obviously that did not answer the
question. That was just another source to say that as a result
of childbirth, the blood could be טהור, tahor, but there's nothing that
tells us that it's only by זבה zivah blood and not by
נדה niddah blood. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. ואיזו זו
קושי בימי נדה. Ve-eizu? Zu koshi bimei niddah.
Very nice, you have a פסוק Pasuk like we said before that
told us that זיבה zivah that that blood as a result of
the fetus is not a problem, but how do you know it's
זיבה zivah blood and not נדה niddah blood? So it says, אלא
אמר אבוה דשמואל אמר קרא. Ela amar Abuha diShmuel amar kra.
Okay, let's try again. The פסוק Pasuk says, forget all those previous
פסוקים, psukim, that's not the basis. Here's what we're going to focus
on. וטמאה שבועים כנדתה. Vetama shevuayim kenidatah.
It says by the case of a woman who gives birth to
a girl, she'll be טמאה tmeiah two weeks as a נדה, niddah,
not that a נדה Niddah is two weeks but it's the same
טומאה tumah as a נדה. niddah. And the point is ולא כזיבתה.
Velo kezivatah.
Why is it that the תורה Torah compared childbirth to the טומאה
tumah of a נדה niddah and not to that of a זבה?
zavah? Now you could say because by a נדה niddah or זבה
zavah it requires seven clean days afterwards, not by a נדה. niddah.
But nevertheless, we're emphasizing here why did it make the comparison altogether?
To somehow say in some ways it's like a נדה niddah and
not like a זבה. zavah. If it was a זבה, zavah, it
would be different. מכלל דזיבתה טהור. Michlal dezivatah tahor.
There are cases where the טומאה tumah is like נדה, niddah, meaning
there are cases. So נדה niddah is about טומאה. tumah. So there
are cases where זיבה zivah might not be about טומאה, tumah, might
be טהור tahor in the context of childbirth pains. I understand. ואיזו
זו קושי בימי זיבה. Ve-eizu? Zu koshi bimei zivah.
That is the when it is a you know birth pains during
the זבה zivah period does not make her a זבה. zavah. So
again the גמרא Gemara really struggling here to find how do you
get this idea. The best פסוק Pasuk to say that it to
learn the general idea I think is the earlier פסוק, Pasuk, דמה.
Damah. It has to be her flow, not resulted from the fetus.
But why then we focus specifically on זבה zavah because here it
says כנדתה, kenidatah, that seems a little bit more difficult. Okay now
the גמרא Gemara goes on. והשתא דכתיב וטמאה שבועים כנדתה
דמה למה לי Vahashta dechsiv vetama shevuayim kenidatah, damah lama li? If
we're not making the דרשה drasha from her flow, her blood, what
do we do with the פסוק Pasuk of her blood? אילא דמה
הוי אמינא כנדתה ולא כזיבתה ואפילו בשופי. Ela damah hava amina kenidatah
velo kezivatah va-afilu be-shofi. Maybe if it hadn't also said the verse
of her blood emphasizing the idea of external cause, I might have
thought that זבה zavah is excluded completely, that whenever a woman is
pregnant any flow will never make her a זבה. zavah. Now by
the way that's not a crazy idea because the idea of זבה
zavah is that it is an unnatural flow and that it might
be some disease or some illness. That's clearly the model the רמב"ם
Rambam pointed out clearly, you know in the תורה, Torah, that it's
in the same way as a זוב zov of a man is
something that's unnatural. So a woman bleeding off-cycle is not the natural
thing. But if she's pregnant there's a a lot of spotting during
pregnancy or potentially. So maybe a woman would never be a זבה
zavah during pregnancy even without being concomitant with the childbirth pains. קמ"ל
Kamasma lan that it's only because of דמה, damah, it's only when
it's directly attributable to the fetus, only when it comes at the
same time of the pains. So this is the דרשה drasha how
we know that bleeding during a connected with birth pains, childbirth, you
know birth pains, pains is not, does not make a woman a
זבה, zavah, but it would still make her a נדה. niddah. Now
we go back to an earlier thing which is what happens, as
we said, this is only when there has not been an interruption,
there has not been a day of no pains. So what do
you do when you don't yet know if there's going to be
an interruption? She has some bleeding with pains, she's pregnant, does she
now, could she assume she's טהורה tehorah or does she have to
be concerned that she might be טמאה temeah because there might be
a break in the birth pains, right? Because we said it's only
when the birth pains continue up to the birth. So they had
a debate at the beginning. רב Rav said she can basically assume
she's טהורה, tehorah, שמואל Shmuel says you have to assume she's טמאה.
temeah. רב Rav said just don't have sex that day, but that
night already you can have sex, you don't have to worry about
what might happen later. So now we're going to see how we
פסקן pasken about that. And it's an interesting little story. Let's take
a look. שילה בר אבינא Shila bar Avina עבד עובדא כוותיה דרב.
avad uvda kevatei de-Rav. שילה בר אבינא Shila bar Avina ruled like
רב. Rav. A woman had one day of bleeding with birth pains
and he said fine, you can assume that the birth pains will
continue, you can have sex that night. Don't have to worry that
there'll be a break.
כי נח נפשיה דרב, ki nach nafshei de-Rav, when רב Rav was
dying, אמר ליה לרב אסי, amar lei le-Rav Asi, he said to
רב אסי Rav Asi who was maybe there by the bed, צניעיה,
tzanyei, go and literally means like hide him but it means but
you know it means like try to cover up that fact that
I ruled, you know, that I ruled that a woman can have
sex that day. Basically, he's reversing himself. I ruled that if she
has birth pains she can assume and bleeds she can assume that
she'll remain טהורה, tehorah, that it won't be a problem later on.
You know what? I'm reversing myself. So go and, I heard that,
this is what apparently he said, this is what he was worried
about on his deathbed. And apparently
he knew that שילה Shila had ruled according to him. So he's
actually telling him go like, you know, hide up, cover over the
fact of what שילה Shila ruled, like try to, you know, don't
publicize it, get it out of the news. I don't want that
to be attributed to me. I don't want that פסק. psak.
Okay, obviously it's attributed to him.
Right. Okay, so anyway, ואי
לא
צאית, ve-i lo tzyit, and if he doesn't listen to me and
if he doesn't listen, גייריה, gayre, then try now. Now רש"י's Rashi's
גרסא girsa is with a ריש. reish. Then try to basically draw
him, convince him that he should reverse himself. Okay. Now רב אסי
Rav Asi סבר savar גדיה. gadye. He thought he misheard him. He
didn't say גייריה gayre with a ריש, reish, he thought he said
גדיה gadye with a דלת dalet which means like cut him off,
which is a harsh term, which means like put him in חרם.
cherem. Now if דוב Dov was here, he'd point out that תוספות
Tosafot says that both גרסאות girsa'ot had גדיה gadye with a דלת
dalet but one was with a דגש dagesh and the other was
without a דגש dagesh and that makes the difference what it means.
But anyway, so he said, you know, try to convince him to
reverse himself, but he thought he had heard him say something more
more harsh. Okay. אמר ליה. amar lei. Okay. גדיה אמר ליה. gadye
amar lei. That's what he thought he said to him. בתר דנח
נפשיה דרב, betar de-nach nafshei de-Rav, after רב Rav died, אמר ליה
הדר בך, amar lei hadar bach, he said reverse yourself דהדר ביה
רב, de-hadar beih Rav, רב Rav reversed himself. So אמר ליה, amar
lei, so
so this is what רב אסי Rav Asi said to שילה. Shila.
So שילה Shila said back to רב אסי, Rav Asi, אמר ליה
אם איתא דהדר ביה, amar lei im ita de-hadar beih, if רב
Rav had reversed himself, לדידי הוה אמר ליה. le-didi hava amar lei.
So he would have told me! Sure. Since he פסקן pasken'd to
me and I went and I פסקן pasken'd accordingly and if he
had reversed himself he would have told me, he would have told
me directly. So of course there were no cell phones at that
time, maybe didn't have a chance, but anyway, לא צאית, lo tzyit,
he refused to listen. So גדיה, gadye, so רב אסי Rav Asi
גדיה gadye which means like cut him off, meaning put him in
חרם. cherem. Okay, which is what he thought רב Rav said to
him.
How often would such a situation have arisen that רב Rav would
have bleeding
as a result of childbirth prior and then
stopping then bleeding as that that particular scenario?
I don't know. I can't imagine that it's that unlikely, right? I
mean a person can have some spotting associated with child pains and
then can go a day without child pains. Is that so unlikely?
So she would have to go to the מקוה mikvah or just
ignore it?
No. So if there was a break then she would have to
go to the מקוה. mikvah. If there was child pains continuous up
to the childbirth then she would not. So that's really the question.
Well then she wouldn't be able to have sex with her husband.
That's the question. But but in if there's going to be continuous
pains she would be able to have sex. So it's not ignored.
If there's going to be a break she has to go to
the מקוה mikvah and it won't be ignored. If it's continuous she
doesn't have to go to the מקוה mikvah and it is ignored.
So and the fact that she might have a break in the
child pains after having child pains for one day with bleeding, I
think is not so uncommon. Now the question is which way is
רב Rav reversing himself? רב Rav said treat she should be like
a נדה niddah for the day, she can have sex that night.
So I would think he's reversing himself, you know, the normal inclination
is to be strict and to be concerned that she might have
a break in the child pains and he's reversing himself to be
strict, which also could mean why he's so insistent, like he's not
he doesn't, you know, he doesn't want people being too lenient about
this. But if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says just
to take a break here for a second, let's see what רש"י
Rashi says. רש"י Rashi says צניעיה tzanyei three lines down in the
wide lines, השתר אותו דבר, hashter oto davar, hide what I said,
אמור לו שיחזור בו, emor lo she-yachzor bo, tell him to reverse
himself, לטהרה לגמרי, le-taharah legamrei, that she can even have sex on
the same day. So רש"י Rashi assumed that he was reversing himself
to be even more lenient, not to be more strict. So it's
not clear which way he was reversing himself. Okay, anyway so let's
see how.
And that's why he said so strongly about?
Yeah, then the question is why would
he
think put him in חרם. cherem. Well, it's a big deal if
you're afraid that somebody might be עובר *over* on an איסור *issur*
of נדה nida *niddah*, which is an איסור כרת issur kares. *issur
kareis*. So then it's a big deal, but if you want to
be, it's an issue about being more lenient for that day itself,
and as you point out, you're not supposed to be having sex
in the daytime anyway. So, well, anyway, so I, that's why the
sense of such anxiety here makes you think that they want to
be more strict, not more lenient. So it's an interesting read of
רש״י *Rashi*. Let's see how the story continues. What about a pregnant
woman who spots? Does she become a זבה zava, *zava* if she
spots during and after her birth?
I understand that this נדה nida *niddah* blood is very...
I understand, but according to the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it does not matter biologically if it's menstruation or
not. The fact that it's uterine blood makes her a נדה nida
*niddah*, and if it comes at a different time period it makes
her a זבה zava, *zava*. So it doesn't matter whether biologically it's
menstrual blood. Okay. The only exception to that rule is if it's
resulting from the fetus during the זבה zava, *zava* period.
Do you understand the basic biology of pregnancy, that נדה niddah, *niddah*
only occurs, that menstruation occurs with failed conception?
I believe so, because they certainly understood that, well, not exactly, no,
not exactly. From the discussions about pregnancy and they understood that women
didn't normally menstruate during pregnancy, but it's not to say it gave
a different reason for it. It gave because she feels heavy and
weighted down, and that impacts her body. So I don't think they
got the basic biology.
If they don't get the basic biology, then it really becomes a
funny discussion.
I understand, but הלכתית *halachically*, for better or
for worse, we don't define colors of blood based on the biological
question of is it really blood; we don't define the question of
when is it bleeding and the cause of the bleeding based on
the question of menstruation. Although I have said in a previous שיעור
*shiur*, and I will get back to it another time, that there
are some אחרונים *acharonim*, notably the ציץ אליעזר *Tzitz Eliezer*, that try
to work it back into a concept of menstruation, and there's important
נפקא מינות *nafka minos* about that. But for now, let's, so today
the הלכה halacha, *halacha* follows the mistaken?
No, there's an, okay, I can't, look, look, let me just say
this and then we'll move on. There's a הלכה halacha *halacha* that
if it's bleeding as a result of a wound, she's not a
נדה niddah *niddah*. So but all other causes, even externally stimulated and
even during pregnancy or whatever, she is a נדה niddah, *niddah*. Now,
the ציץ אליעזר *Tzitz Eliezer* tries to expand the category of wound
to include many cases in which it's not basically menstrual bleeding even
though it's not really a wound. Okay, so that's where the interesting
discussion is nowadays, how much do you sort of try to get
it into a category of what we know to be menstrual bleeding.
But let's just leave it there. There's a basic question we still
have to understand, because
we're saying this has to be the שלשה ימים בתוך אחד עשר
יום *shlosha yamim betoch achas asar yom*, right? Right.
But she has to have bled already before, right? Right.
So that's one of the things. And also, it's kind of harsh,
she's been pregnant for close to nine months or however long this
is, if this is already getting birth pangs or this is something
really early. How would she know when her נדה niddah *niddah* is
or י״א יום *yud aleph yom* is?
If she bleeds once after more than eighteen days since her last
time she was a נדה niddah, *niddah*, which was like
six months ago, then that first bleeding makes her a נדה niddah,
*niddah*. Then if she bleeds again within the ימים *yamim*, the days
eight to eighteen, then that could make her a זבה zava, *zava*.
But you're right, this is a rare case. It's pretty darn rare.
So she would have to have bled twice and the second bleeding
within the eleven days after, that is correct.
So that's why it's odd that on his deathbed, I understand, but
that's why he asks him often. It's a very odd situation that
he should be plagued with getting it right as he's dying.
You don't know what the scenario was. Maybe רב אסי Rav Asi
*Rav Asi* was telling him on his deathbed: Do you know what
שילא Shila *Sheila* is saying in your name? Or maybe two days
before. In that case, he might have had a rare case for
the first time. All right, let's see anyway, but I think it's
particularly interesting according to רש״י *Rashi* that his concern is that you
be more lenient. Okay, let's take a look. So שילא Shila *Sheila*
refused to reverse himself. לא la, ציית *lo tzai*, he didn't listen.
גדייה *gadye*, so he cut him off. אמר ליה Amar lei, *amar
lei*, שילא Shila *Sheila* said to רב אסי Rav Asi *Rav Asi*:
ולא
מסתפי מר מגחלתא *velo mistafi mar miguchalta*? Are you not afraid from
the fire? That you'll be, as רש״י *Rashi* says, you'll be burnt
by my
ember, it's like a
metaphor, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says be careful with the כבוד kavod
*kavod* of חכמים Chachamim, *chakhamim* lest you be burnt by their fire,
by their embers. So how do you treat
me so lightly that you put me in, so you just down
put me in חרם cherem. *cherem* because of this? So I don't
believe that רב Rav *Rav* reversed himself. So you're not afraid of
me? אמר ליה Amar lei, *amar lei*, he said, how do you
think I'm afraid of you? אני איסי Isi. בן יהודה *ani Issi
ben Yehuda*, דהוא איסי Isi בן גור אריה Ari *d'hu Issi ben
Gur Aryeh*, יהודה ליב *Yehuda Leib*, יהודה אריה *Yehuda Aryeh*, whatever, apparently
that was already back then, okay, so I'm a son of a
lion, דהוא איסי Isi בן גמליאל *d'hu Issi ben Gamliel*, and apparently
he had a lot of names going back to grandparents or otherwise,
no, no, but he is איסי *Issi*, so again, he treats the
name he gave himself, maybe he attributed himself to different people up
his lineage, דהוא איסי בן מהללאל *d'hu Issi ben Mahalalel*. מהללאל. So
anyway, I'm איסי. אסיטא דנחשא Asita De-Nechasha I am a bronze mortar
דלא de-lo שליט בי רקבא, shalit bei rikva, that no mold, you
know, rot can take hold of. So I'm not afraid of your
fire, it's like rock, paper, scissors. Okay? I'm not afraid of your
fire, I'm copper. So I'm איסי which is a copper, there's a
play on the word אסיטא דנחשא Asita De-Nechasha is like copper, copper
as- איסי and אסיטא. Asita. I'm a pest- I'm a mortar and
I'm made out of copper and you can't do anything to- I'm
not afraid of your fire. אמר ליה, amar lei, so שילא Shila
said back to him, ואנא שילא בר אבינא, Va-ana Shila Bar Avina,
and I'm שילא Shila, son of אבינא, Avina, בוכנא, Buchna, there seems
to be a play אבינא, Avina, בוכנא, Buchna, you see it's pretty
close, it's almost the exact- if you make a ב bet into
a כ, chaf, it's like the same letters root worked around. בוכנא
דפרזלא, Buchna De-Parzela, an iron pestle, דמתבר אסיטא דנחשא de-mitbar Asita De-Nechasha
that I can break your bronze mortar, you know, you bang the
pestle against the mortar. So it's really rock, paper, scissors. I'm not
afraid of you. Okay, so then that reminds me of a- of
a rabbinic exchange. Rabbis had fun sometimes. That it was the שאגת
אריה, Shagas Aryeh, you know, his name is שאגת אריה, Shagas Aryeh,
the Roar of the Lion. So he was having a whole big
debate with the משכנות יעקב Mishkenos Yaakov about something, and at the
end of his letter he wrote אריה שאג מי לא ירא, Ari
Shag Mi Lo Yira, right from the פסוק pasuk that an אריה-
a lion roars, who will not be afraid? So then the משכנות
יעקב Mishkenos Yaakov wrote back his response and at the end he
wrote אריה שאג מ"י Mem-Yud לא ירא. Lo Yira. So משכנות יעקב,
Mishkenos Yaakov, okay, you got to get that- it was the משכנות
יעקב Mishkenos Yaakov that מ"י Mem-Yud לא ירא. Lo Yira. So anyway,
gone back from the fact they are not arguing on- they're not
bringing הלכה, halacha it's all their egos. At this point it's my
father is bigger than your father and they've gone so beyond what
the הלכה halacha. should be of bringing fruits right? And so then
they're arguing like- like little boys, you know my father... Well, yeah,
no you're right, you're right, but it's in response to a non-halachic
thing because the- what רב אסי Rav Asi did is he just
put him into חרם. cherem, He didn't have a discussion with him,
שמי, shamei, שהם... shoham... You know what, I- you know what, I
think you make an excellent point which I just realized, which is
exactly true because the- because רב Rav first said is צני, tsanei,
which רב Rav first said is you know, well actually you know,
right, maybe try to persuade him, but- or well maybe it's a
question about משרי, misharei, גרייה gareiyei means more persuade him. But that's
maybe partly the point that you know he didn't do what רב
Rav was saying, which is trying to have a reasonable conversation with
him. He just right away moved into this putting him into חרם,
cherem which led to this- you know, this strong reaction. But you're
right, that's exactly what they didn't do, they didn't do what רב
Rav said which was to try to have a persuasive argument. Okay,
so let's see how this ends. חלש רב אסי, Chalash Rav Asi,
so רב אסי Rav Asi who was putting him into חרם cherem
and שילא Shila was not happy with it, right? So רב אסי
Rav Asi got- got sick and he fell ill. עיילוה לחמימי, Aylu
le-chamimei, talk about being burnt, so- אפקוהו מקרירי, afkouei mi-karirei, עיילוהו בקרירי,
aylu be-karirei, אפקוהו מחמימי. afkouei mi-chamimei. So they put him in hot
water to get rid of the chills, they put him in cold
water to get rid of the heat fever, so you know they
were constantly trying to do different things to- to deal with his
illness. And in the end, נח נפשיה דרב אסי, nach nafshei de-Rav
Asi, he passed away, maybe from these- attempts at these overly vigorous
attempts at healing him. Anyway, he passed away as a result of
this. Now what is שילא Shila going to respond? So אזל azar
שילא, so שילא went, אמר לדובשייה amar le-duvshayei he said to his
wife, צובי לי זבדא דזבדא, tsuvi li zavda de-zavda, prepare for me
my shrouds. For me? For me. Okay, he saw that רב אסי
Rav Asi died as a result of this whole fight, and maybe
רב Rav אסי Asi, started it, but שילא didn't do anything to-
to help it. So he says to his wife go prepare for
me my shrouds. Now why? דלא ליתבי לימא ליה לרב מילי עילוי
ועיי, delo leisvei leimalyei le-Rav mili ilei va'ai, because רב אסי Asi,
is about to go up to heaven and I don't want him
to- to tattle on me to רב and say to רב that
I refused to listen and that I didn't do the right thing
and that I poskened incorrectly. So- now, but maybe that also is
a way of saying that I don't... What? I want to go
up and defend myself! That's what it sounds like on the surface,
but one wonders if it's really just a way of saying I
don't know, let's see what- let's see how it ends. צוביתו ליה
זבדיתא, Tsuviso lei zavdisa, so she prepared for him his shrouds. נח
נפשיה דשילא, Nach nafshei de-Shila, and then he died. חזו דפרחא אסא,
Chazu de-parcha asa, now people saw that- one wonders if that's also
the אסי, אסא Asa and אסי, right, if that- a myrtle was
flying. And צבית ליה זוודתא, tzvise lei zavdasa, so she prepared for
him his shrouds. נח נפשיה דבי שילא, nach nafshe dei bei Shila,
and then he died. חזו, Chazu, now people saw דפרחה אסא, deparcha
asa, one wonders if that's also the אסא, asa, אסא asa and
אסא, asa, right? If that's a myrtle was flying, yes, הדס, hadas,
הדס, hadas, is that not a myrtle? Yes, yeah. That was flying
מהאי פורייה להאי פורייה me'hai puraya le'hai puraya from this coffin to
that coffin, literally this bed to that bed, whether it was over
the graves, it was some type of a vision that people had,
but they saw some myrtle passing between the two graves. So אמרי,
amri, people said, שמע מינה, shma mina, שמע מינה עבדו רבנן פייסא,
shma mina avdu rabanan paisa, we see that the rabbis made peace.
So he died, he went up, they all spoke Torah, they all
made peace up in heaven and therefore the myrtle was flying back
and forth. I am not sure what the real הלכה halacha was.
Right, I mean according to the Gemara's version Rav reversed himself, but
the irony is that we don't know which way he reversed, and
they know it in heaven but לא בשמים. lo bashamayim. Right. Anyway,
but we'd, so, all right, anyway, so, this has some interesting theological,
yes it does, implications, you know, could, I don't know what to
make of this. Okay, but this sort of kills off all these
rabbis. Basically. Okay, but one does wonder if when he said to
his wife, because at that time although he framed it as I
don't want him to say bad things about me, he saw a
realization that he was to blame as well, you know, and in
the end the fact that there was some symbol that they had
made peace, obviously, you know, you know, is sort of I think
like a hopeful way of imagining that in the end, you know,
they both realized that they were in the wrong. Other stories like
this? To some degree, yeah, this is not about the rabbis being
מקפיד makpid on their כבוד and putting people in חרם and that's
definitely a theme, yeah, a trope I might say. All right, now
the גמרא Gemara continues, ל"ז עמוד א', lamed zayin amud alef, about
five lines down. בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, now we get back to
הלכה. halacha, Okay, בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, קושי koshi מהו שתסתור בזיבה?
mahu she-tistor be-ziva? Now that we said that if a woman bleeds
and with the child pains, קושי, koshi, that it does not make
her a זבה, zava let's say it's not a question of making
her a זבה, ziva but will it interrupt her seven clean days?
A woman was a זבה, zava, she had, she bled during her
pregnancy without the child pains, and now she's counting seven clean days
and now she bleeds with child pains. Does the blood that's coming
with the pains, that can't make her a זבה, zava? is it
still enough to interrupt her clean days if she's counting clean days?
So what's the conceptual question? דבר המטמא סותר, davar ha-metame soter, do
we say that something that causes טומאה, tumah, the blood is still
זבה zava blood and it still causes טומאה, tumah, so therefore it
interrupts the clean days. והאי נמי מטמא בימי נדה, ve-hai nami metame
bimei nida, and this also causes טומאה, tumah, maybe not this blood
per se causes טומאה, tumah, but if a woman were to bleed
with child pains during her נדה period, then that would cause טומאה.
tumah. So although this blood itself is טהור, tahor, I think I
might have said בימי נדה. bimei nida. It should be בימי. bimei.
I think it is בימי. bimei. I don't know, yeah. ניסויים. nisuyim.
Yeah, okay, anyway, right, בימי נדה. bimei nida. So this blood itself
that comes with קושי koshi during זבה zava. period, doesn't make her
a זבה, ziva it itself is טהור, tahor, but were it to
come during her נדה period it would be טמא. tamei. So is
the fact that it is potentially טמא tamei in a different context
enough to interrupt the זבה? zava Already you could say who cares
about potential, but anyway that's one possibility. או דילמא, o dilma, or
do we say דבר הגורם סותר והאי לאו גורם הוא. davar ha-gorem
soter ve-hai lav gorem hu. The only thing that interrupts the clean
days of a זבה zava. is bleeding that could make her into
a זבה. zava, The reason it interrupts the זבה zavah? period is
because this is זבה zavah blood, it's blood that could make her
into a זבה. zava, So if this type of blood with pain
might make her into a נדה but will never make her into
a זבה, zava, it should not interrupt the clean days. That's his
question. אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so Abaye said, אונס בזיבה
יוכיח. ones be-ziva yochiach. I'll bring you a proof. אונס ones by
a flow, not here the woman's flow, but a man's flow. Okay,
you might remember we learned a few days ago that a man
only when he has this unnatural flow not due to external causes
is he a זב, zav, but after he's a זב zav three
times and then he needs seven clean days, if he has an
unnatural flow even as an אונס, ones, even not even due to
external causes, that interrupts the clean days. So there's your answer. A
flow that would not make him a זב zav interrupts his clean
days. So אונס בזיבה יוכיח שאינו גורם, ones be-ziva yochiach she-eino gorem,
the flow for the man which is as a result of an
external cause does not make him a זב, zav, וסותר, ve-soter, and
it interrupts the clean days. אמר amar ליה, לא, lo, who says?
האי נמי גורם הוא. hai nami gorem hu. I'll claim that that
actually makes him a, even an unnatural flow makes him a, makes
him a זב. zav. How could that be? דתנן, de-tanan, we taught
in a Mishnah. ראיה ראשונה, re'iya rishona, the man saw the first
flow. בודקין אותו, bodkin oto, you check to make sure that there's
no external causes that were result of it. שניה בודקין אותו, shniya
bodkin oto, the second one you make sure that no external causes.
שלישית אין בודקין אותו, shlishis ein bodkin oto, the third one you
don't bother checking him. The third one that leads to him bringing
a קרבן korban and a full-fledged זב, zav, even if it's due
to external causes. So he said a flow of אונס ones by
a man, it does have impact for him being a זב, zav,
from being a זב zav of two ראיות re'iyos to three, a
זב zav who brings a קרבן. korban. So it's not like it's
a flow that does not make him a זב. zav. It does
make him a higher level זב. zav. Okay, so they made it
based on דרשות, drashos, we learned it before. Okay, so that's what
he said. I actually say that it does have. So גמרא Gemara
says one minute, ולרבי אליעזר דאמר אף בשלישי בודקין אותו הכא נמי
כיון דלא גרע לא סתר. U'le'Rabbi Eliezer de'amar af bishlishi bodkin oto
hacha nami kivan delo gara lo satar. So one minute, but רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that even to bring a קרבן, korban, all
three flows cannot be based on external causes. So would you say
according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that there's never a flow of
אונס oness by a man that makes him a זב zav that
has any implication making him a זב? zav? Would you say that
it does not interrupt the seven clean days? So אמר amar ליה,
לרבי אליעזר הכי נמי. le'Rabbi Eliezer hachi nami. Yes, that's what I
would say. According to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that doesn't have any
weight of a flow of an external flow, it would not interrupt
the clean days. תא שמע, ta shema, let me try and prove
against this. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אף בשלישי בודקין אותו,
af bishlishi bodkin oto, the third time you check the man to
make sure no external causes. ברביעית אין בודקין אותו, birvi'it ein bodkin
oto, by the fourth flow it doesn't matter. So you see, the
fourth flow means a flow that's going to interrupt the seven clean
days. And at that stage, even if it's אונס, oness, it still
interrupts. מאי לאו לסתירה? mai lav lestira? Don't you see that it
can interrupt even if it stays on an external flow? I mean,
even if it's based on an external cause. לא, לטמויי לההיא טיפא
במשא. letimuei lahu tipa bemasa. So that's a very weak response. He
says no, when he says the fourth one, if it's אונס oness
doesn't matter, it does not mean that that fourth one interrupts the
seven days. It means the fourth one is טמא. tamei. Remember like
the idea like his spit is טמא, tamei, so his flow is
טמא. tamei. So the semen, not the semen, the fluid, the flow
itself is itself טמא tamei that if you carry it you become
טמא. tamei. But it does not interrupt the clean days. So let's
just take a step back. What are we saying now? We're trying
to say, does a woman's flow of blood with the קושי koshi
interrupt her clean days if it cannot make her a זבה? zava
We're trying to argue by analogy by a man whose his flow
that makes him a זב zav is only when it's not אונס,
oness, when it's not external causes. Would a flow of אונס oness
interrupt? And the argument is, look, we see that it does interrupt,
a flow of אונס. oness. And the גמרא Gemara has two answers.
Either that's because maybe a flow of אונס oness can partly make
him a זב, zav, or we're trying to deny that. No, it
doesn't really interrupt the clean days. It really just is that the
thing itself is טמא. tamei. Okay, but גמרא Gemara is not satisfied.
תא שמע, ta shema, come in here, I will prove to you
that that's really it really does interrupt. בשלישית רבי אליעזר אומר בודקין
אותו, bishlishit Rabbi Eliezer omer bodkin oto, ברביעית אין בודקין אותו. birvi'it
ein bodkin oto. Here's a fuller ברייתא. braita. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says don't bother checking in the fourth flow, it doesn't matter if
it's an אונס. oness. Why? לקרבן אמרתי ולא לסתירה. le'korban amarti velo
lestira. I only say that that אונס oness matters to bring him
to a level of bringing a קרבן. korban. But when it comes
to סתירה, stira, interrupting the clean days, then even if it's an
אונס, oness, it can interrupt. So here you have an explicit statement.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says a flow of אונס oness cannot make
him a זב zav to any degree. One, two, and three cannot
be based on אונס. oness. But to interrupt, even a flow of
אונס. oness. So you see, according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, a
flow that does not make him a זב zav can interrupt the
clean days. And we by analogy we should argue the same by
a woman. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא לרבי אליעזר
תיפשוט. ela le'Rabbi Eliezer tipshot. For רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you definitely
can conclude דדבר שאינו גורם, de'davar she'eino gorem, even something that cannot
make him a זב, zav, meaning a flow of אונס, oness, סותר
soter can still interrupt the clean days. ולרבנן מאי? u'le'rabbanan mai? But
we still don't know according to the רבנן. rabbanan. The רבנן rabbanan
say a flow even of אונס oness has significance to make him
a זב. zav. So we still don't know according to the רבנן
rabbanan that argue on רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, can a flow that
does not make a person a זב zav or זבה zava, interrupt
the clean days? So גמרא Gemara says תא שמע, ta shema, come
in here, דתני אבוה דרבי אבין, detani avuha de'Rabbi Avin, the father
of רבי אבין Rabbi Avin taught a ברייתא, braita, מה גרם לו
זובו שבעה, ma garam lo zovo shiva, what cause what does his
זוב zov flow cause the man to become, a seven day טומאה.
tumah. לפיכך, lefichach, therefore if you see this זוב zov flow during
your seven days of clean your clean days, סותר שבעה, soter shiva,
you have to start the seven all over again because the power
of the זיבה ziva flow is to create a טומאה tumah of
seven days. מה גרם לו קריו יום אחד, ma garam lo keryo
yom echad, however a seminal emission, what type of טומאה tumah is
caused by a seminal emission, יום אחד, yom echad, just one day.
לפיכך, lefichach, therefore if you have a seminal emission during your seven
clean days, סותר יום אחד, soter yom echad, it interrupts one day
but not all seven days. So this is a general principle we've
seen before that if a man bleeds, bleeds, if a man has
a זוב zov emission during the seven clean days, you have to
start all over again, but a seminal emission you only lose the
one day connected to the degree of טומאה tumah that they cause.
But the fact that he uses the phrase מה גרם לו, ma
garam lo, what does this flow cause him to be, it causes
him to be a זב, zav, a seven day זב, zav, emphasizes
that the power of interruption is based on what it causes, that
can make you into a זב. zav. So the גמרא Gemara just
says from that choice of language, although the הלכה halacha doesn't prove
it, but the choice of language proves that connected conceptually to whether
it causes you to be a זב. zav. So it says if
he carries one of those days of your seven clean just have
to count one more clean? Correct. Correct. The same way by a
פולטת שכבת זרע, poletet shichvat zera, we did we had that before.
So the גמרא Gemara says, where are we? מאי שבעה? mai shiva?
What do you mean, why is it why does the flow of
seven interrupt seven days? What does it mean that a flow causes
seven? אילימא דמטמאה שבעה, ilima demetama shivah, if it says, if it's
just that it causes a seven-day טומאה, tumah, so then it should
have said האי מה זבה ומטמאה שבעה hai ma zava u-metama shivah
מיבעי ליה. mibaye lei. It should have said his flow causes a
seven-day טומאה, tumah, therefore it interrupts seven days. That's the term he
should have used. אלא לאו, ela lav, the fact that he didn't
say a seven-day טומאה, tumah, but he says it causes you to
be a זב, zav, we see he's telling us the principle דבר
הגורם סותר, davar hagorem soter, only a flow that can cause you
to be a זב zav can interrupt the seven days. דבר שאינו
גורם, davar she-eino gorem, if it cannot cause you to be a
זב, zav, אינו סותר, eino soter, does not interrupt. שמע מינה. shema
mina. And now we have created a debate that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says that a flow of אונס ones can never make you
a זב, zav, but it can interrupt. So for him, a flow
that does not make you it can interrupt the period. For however
the חכמים, the language here of גורם, gorem, that זוב zuv causes,
גורם, gorem, the flow is גורם, gorem, tells us that no, only
if the flow can cause you to be a זב zav can
it interrupt, and therefore the relevant for the woman is that bleeding
as a result of קושי, koshi, the childbirth pains, since it can
never make her into a זבה, zava, can never interrupt the days
of the seven clean days. And now the גמרא Gemara concludes with
that, אמר אביי נקטינן, amar Abaye naktinan, therefore we take as the
הלכה, halacha אין קושי סותר בזיבה, ein koshi soter be-ziva, that bleeding
as a result of childbirth pains does not interrupt the seven clean
days because it cannot make her a זבה, zava that although in
other scenarios it can be טמא, tamei, but since it can never
make her a זבה zava, it cannot interrupt. ואי משכחת תנא דאמר
סותר, ve-i meshkachat tanna de-amar soter, if you ever find anybody that
says that it does interrupt the clean days even though it cannot
make her into a זבה, zava? רבי אליעזר היא, Rabbi Eliezer hi,
it's the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that we saw said something similar
by a man that a flow of אונס ones that doesn't make
him a זב zav can still interrupt the seven clean days. So
this is the principle that the only thing that can interrupt is
דבר הגורם סותר, davar hagorem soter, only thing that can cause the
טומאה. tumah. Now I should mention by the way, because we mentioned
last time, an important הלכה halacha. that we had a few days
ago was the fact of a woman פולטת שכבת זרע poletet shichvat
zera whose semen comes out of her body, does that stop her
from counting the clean days? And based on various ways in which
that הלכה halacha, is learned and then later sort of greater stringencies
are and laws are placed on it, that's why nowadays for אשכנזים,
Ashkenazim, women don't start counting their seven clean days until day six
based on concerns that they might have had תשמיש tashmish before and
semen came out of the body and so on and that would
prevent them from counting some of the days as clean days. But
one question that gets asked and רש"י Rashi himself asks it is
how does that fit with the principle that we just concluded that
דבר הגורם סותר, davar hagorem soter, that the only thing that can
interrupt a woman's clean days are the things that can make a
woman into a זבה, zava right? So how does that thing fit
that principle? So רש"י'ס Rashi's answer is no, no, that's only to
interrupt all seven days, to start all over again. But if you're
only just not counting the one day it doesn't have to satisfy
that criteria. But some ראשונים Rishonim are actually very bothered by that.
So this is part of the whole question that goes into that
very important הלכתי halachic issue around פולטת שכבת זרע. poletet shichvat zera.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara moves on to a related topic, but
we're done with this topic of דבר הגורם סותר. davar hagorem soter.
תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Beraita, רב מרינוס אומר, Rav
Merinos omer, רב מרינוס Rav Merinos says, אין לידה סותרת בזיבה. ein
leida soteret be-ziva. So the actual if a woman is counting, became
a זבה zavah, right before she gave birth, it wasn't with קושי,
koshi, so she had bleeding without קושי, koshi, she became a זבה,
zavah, and she's counting her clean days and now she had childbirth.
Okay, there's a lot of blood in childbirth. Okay, does that interrupt
her seven clean days? And his answer is no, that is not
דם dam of נדה, it's not the normal type of דם, dam,
it's childbirth blood. So childbirth blood does not interrupt her clean days
and she can go ahead and after that bleeding stops, presumably she
can't count those days, but after those bleeding stops she can continue
counting her clean days. Pretty amazing הלכה. halacha, Now we have another
question though. איבעיא להו, ibaya lehu, מהו שתעלה? mahu she-taaleh? How about
during that week or two weeks that she's טמאה, temea, if she's
not bleeding, can those days of טומאה tumah without blood count towards
her seven clean days? We have had this before, but question is
ימי לידה שאינה רואה בהן yemei leida she-eina roah bahen are they
עולים לספירת זיבתה olim li-sfirat zivatah or not? The days of childbirth,
the week or the two weeks of טומאה tumah that has no
bleeding, can those count towards her clean days if she happens to
be a זבה? zavah, Now this הלכה, halacha although it sounds very
obscure, actually has practical implications as I said. A woman could miscarry
and it could be a girl, so that means two weeks of
טומאה, tumah, and it could be that she stops bleeding before those
two weeks are up. You'd say לידה, leida, that's not... No, but
לידה leida includes miscarriage. Remember we had a whole פרק perek about
once it's forty days, it's the טומאה tumah of לידה. leida. Once
it's... So a childbirth wouldn't be... Right, right, but that's why I'm
saying in a case of a miscarriage you can have a woman
could have clean days before the two weeks are up and we
treat every woman nowadays essentially as a זבה zavah as requiring seven
clean days. Can she start counting her clean days before the two
weeks are up? So that's this הלכה, halacha ימי לידה שאינה רואה
בהם, yemei leida she-eina roah bahem, are they עולים לספירת זיבתה olim
li-sfirat zivatah or not? Why are we asking for sources here? Because
before this is the base where it's discussed, before it was assumed,
here it's discussed. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
that's the question. מה שתלה, Ma she-tala, אביי Abaye אמר אינה סותרת
ואינה עולה. amar eina soteret v'eina olah. No, the days of טומאה
tumah of the לידה leida days don't interrupt the seven clean days,
but you can't count them. רבא Rava אמר אינה סותרת ועולה. amar
eina soteret v'olah. It doesn't interrupt and actually counts as long as
you're not bleeding, even though you're טמא tamei because of יולדת, yoledet,
it counts towards the clean days. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מנא אמינא
לה, m'na amina lah, where do I know this from? דתניא, detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, Braita, ואחר תטהר, v'achar tithar, afterwards she'll
be pure. This is about a זבה, zavah. seven clean days. אחר
אחד או אחר אחר לכולן, achar echad o achar achar l'chullan, one
unit of seven days, שלא תהא טומאה מפסקת ביניהם, she-lo tehei tumah
mafseket beineihem, there's no טומאה tumah that interrupts them. אי אמרת בשלמא
עולה, ei amart bishlama olah, if you say that the days of
childbirth without bleeding can count, היינו דלא מפסקא טומאה, hainu d'lo mafseka
tumah, there's no interruption of טומאה. tumah. אלא אי אמרת אינה עולה,
אפסק ליה לידה, ela ei amart eina olah afseq lei leida, so
how can you count, meaning if you had three days that are
of your seven before childbirth, then you took a two-week break because
you can't count that whole two weeks of childbirth, and then you
started counting again, how you consider that a unit of seven days?
There's this period in between that can never count. According to me,
he says, maybe the first day or two or three you can't
count because there's bleeding, but at least this is not a period
that is sort of excluded, you know, sort of a clear break,
because the other days could count, so it doesn't break the days
before and the day after. It's a period where days can count
towards the טהרה tahara days. But according to you that this whole
week or two weeks can never count, why how come it doesn't
break up the before and the after? So he says, אלא אי
אמרת אינה עולה ela ei amart eina olah, אפסק ליה לידה, afseq
lei leida, the לידה leida interrupts it. אמר לך אביי, Amar lach
Abaye, אביי Abaye would say to you, שלא תהא טומאת זיבה מפסקת
ביניהם. she-lo tehei tumat zivah mafseket beineihem. No, this is לידה leida
טומאה. tumah. It's true that you can't count those days towards the
זבה, zavah but since the woman is not a זבה, zavah, it
does not, that is not considered to break up the unit of
seven days. Only a bleeding that would make her a זבה zavah
would break up the unit of seven days. Okay, so that's not
a proof. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava is going to
try again. מנא אמינא לה, m'na amina lah, where do I know
it from? דתניא, detanya, we taught in another ברייתא, Braita, we quoted
this yesterday, מזובה, mizovah, from her flow, מזובה ולא מנגעה, mizovah v'lo
minega'ah, maybe we didn't quote this yesterday, excuse me, from her flow
and not if she is a, and we don't have to worry
if she has a נגע, nega, she's a מצורע. metzora. A woman
is a מצורעת, metzora'at, she can still go to the מקוה mikveh
and get rid of her זבות zavut state. Okay, the fact that
she's also מצורעת metzora'at does not prevent her from becoming טהור tahor
as from being a זבה. zavah Okay, so it says מזובה, mizovah,
from her flow she can go to the מקוה, mikveh, ולא מלידתה,
v'lo milleidatah, even if and she doesn't have to be טהור tahor
from her לידה leida state. So a woman can actually go to
the מקוה, mikveh, become, even though she had this period of לידה,
leida, and be טהור, tahor, even though she was counting her seven
days, it seems like it's saying during her period of being a
יולדת. yoledet. Okay, now it doesn't actually mean that she can go
to the מקוה, mikveh, because a woman the טומאה tumah of צרעת
tzara'at and the טומאה tumah of זבה zavah are like, you know,
unrelated. So you can go to the מקוה mikveh for מצורע metzora
without for זבה, zavah but זבה zavah and לידה, leida, you obviously
have to have sex with her husband. Okay, but the טומאה tumah
of זבה zava and the טומאה tumah of יולדת yoledet are still
within that same world of טומאה tumah and you can't be a
non-זבה zava but yet be, like, what's also what's the נפקא מינה?
nafka mina? So רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean in that case
she can go to the מקוה, mikveh, but it means that even
though she's a יולדת, yoledet, it doesn't have to stop her from
counting her clean days. So that's an explicit ruling like רבא. Rava.
אמר לך אביי, Amar lach Abaye, so אביי Abaye would say back
to you, תני חדא, tani chada, all right, so switch the text
of the ברייתא. Braita. מזובה ולא מנגעה, mizovah v'lo minega'ah, don't have
both cases. Really the ברייתא Braita ended that it doesn't matter that
she's a מצורע. metzora. ולא תיתני ולא מלידתה, v'lo titni v'lo milleidatah,
and don't have the second phrase. It does matter if she just
gave birth, she can't count the clean days. Cut out those words
from the ברייתא. Braita. ורבא, V'Rava, רבא Rava would say back to
you, האי מאי, hai mai, what are you talking about? אי אמרת
בשלמא מזובה ולא מלידתה, ei amart bishlama mizovah v'lo milleidatah, if we
have the phrase telling us that even when she's a יולדת yoledet
she can count her clean days, so that is a real הלכה
halacha that you need to teach. היינו דאיצטריך ליה לידה, hainu d'itztarich
lei leida, since it needed to teach the הלכה halacha of childbirth
that she can count those days as clean days, תני נגע, tani
nega, we taught the הלכה halacha of being a מצורע metzora even
though that's pretty obvious, of course you can go to the מקוה
mikveh for a זבה zava. if you're a מצורע, metzora, they're unrelated.
אטו לידה, atu leida, since we're talking about the לידה leida case.
אלא אי אמרת מזובה ולא מנגעה ela ei amart mizovah v'lo minega'ah
is the only thing you teach, that she can go to the
מקוה mikveh as a זבה zava and it doesn't matter that she's
a מצורע, metzora, why do I need to teach me that? האי
מכדי טהר הזב מזובו נפקא, hai michdi tihar ha-zav mizovo nafka, we
can learn it out from the exact same thing we say by
a זב. zav. What's the דרשה drasha we say by a זב?
zav? When the זב zav becomes טמא tamei from his flow, מזובו
ולא מנגעו, mizovo v'lo minega'o, from his flow and it doesn't matter
that he still is a מצורע. metzora. So we have that הלכה
halacha by a man, so we wouldn't bother telling it to me
by a woman. If we're going to tell me by a woman,
it's only to tell me the new הלכה halacha that it doesn't
matter that she's a יולדת yoledet and that you can even count
those days. ואביי, V'Abaye, אביי Abaye would say back to you, חד
בזב וחד בזבה וצריכא, chad b'zav v'chad b'zavah v'tzricha, no, one is
by a זב, zav, we have to tell me both by a
man and by a woman that it doesn't matter that they're מצורע.
metzora. דאי כתב רחמנא *De-ei kasav rachmana*, this is a general thing
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that you can't necessarily learn זב *zav*
from זבה zava *zavah*, each one has its own stringencies. דאי כתב
רחמנא בזב *De-ei kasav rachmana bezav*, had it just said by a
man that he can go to the מקוה *mikvah* even though he's
still a מצורע *metzora* משום דלא מטמא באונס *mishum delo mitamei be-ones*,
it's a more lenient category as we saw, a man does not
become a זב *zav* if it's based on an external cause, אונס
*ones*. אבל זבה zava. דמטמיא באונס *Aval zavah dematmiya be-ones*, a woman
who becomes a זבה *zavah* even based on external causes, אונס *ones*,
אימא לא *eima lo*, that's more strict, so maybe she can't go
to the מקוה *mikvah* if she's a מצורע *metzora*. צריכא *Tzricha*, so
it has to tell me by a woman as well. ואי כתב
רחמנא בזבה *V'ei kasav rachmana bezavah*, had it just said זבה *zavah*,
משום דלא מטמיא בראיות כבימים *mishum delo mitmiya bireiyos kevyamim*, in one
way a זבה *zavah* is more lenient, if a זבה *zavah* has
three flows on the same day she's not a זבה *zavah*, she
has to have three flows on three separate days consecutive days, okay,
that's more lenient, that's only in that scenario. אבל זב דמטמא בראיות
כבימים *Aval zav demitamei bireiyos kevyamim*, a זב *zav* has three flows
regardless of whether it's on three days or not or one day
or whatever, so that's more strict, אימא לא *eima lo*, maybe he
can't go to the מקוה *mikvah* if he's a מצורע *metzora*, צריכא
*tzricha*, it needs to tell me both. So אביי Abaye *Abaye* says
I take the words out of that ברייתא braisa *braisa*, it's not
that since she's a יולדת yoledes *yoledet* she cannot count those days
towards being her clean days and all the ברייתא *braisa* saying is
instead she's a מצורע *metzora* she can still go to the מקוה
*mikvah* for being a זב *zav*. So רבא Rava *Rava*'s proofs were
answered by אביי Abaye *Abaye*, although again the text to the ברייתא
*braisa* as רבא Rava, *Rava* had it clearly was explicit like רבא
Rava *Rava*. אמר amar, אביי Abaye *Amar Abaye*, now אביי *Abaye* gets
in his licks. מנא אמינא לה *Mena amina lah*, where do I
know it from that she can't count those days? דתניא *Detanya*, we
taught in a ברייתא *braisa*. דבותה תטמא *Devosah sitma*, that this we
quoted this ברייתא *braisa* before about a woman who gave birth, her
flow during like the days of her flow she will be טמא
tamei. *tamei*. לרבות את בועלה *Lerabbos es boalah*, that a יולדת yoledes
*yoledet* just like a נדה *niddah*, a man who has sex with
a נדה *niddah* he becomes טמא *tamei*, a man who has sex
with a woman who's a יולדת yoledes, *yoledet* he becomes טמא *tamei*.
דבותה תטמא *Devosah sitma*, of her flow she'll be טמא *tamei*. לרבות
את הלילות *Lerabbos es haleilos*, even the nights because the תורה Torah
*Torah* says days shall be טמא *tamei*, you know, שבעת ימים *shivas
yamim*, so in order to counter the word of days in the
תורה Torah *Torah*, here it also includes even nights. Okay, that's not
our focus. The last one is our focus. דבותה תטמא *Devosah sitma*,
during her flow she is טמא *tamei*. לרבות את היולדת בזוב *Lerabbos
es hayoledes bezov*, to include the case of a woman who gave
birth while she was a זבה *zavah*, שצריכה שתשב שבעה נקיים *she-tzricha
she-teitchev shiva nekiyim*, she needs to still get her שבעה נקיים *shiva
nekiyim*. So אביי *Abaye* says what does it mean? Of course she
needs to get her שבעה נקיים *shiva nekiyim*. So it must be
telling me that her שבעה נקיים *shiva nekiyim* can't be counted during
this period, this is a טמא *tamei* period and it can't count
towards the שבעה נקיים *shiva nekiyim*. מאי לאו נקיים מלידה *Mai lav
nekiyim milieda*, doesn't it mean that she has to get out of
her לידה leida? *lieda* period to count her שבעה נקיים *shiva nekiyim*?
לא מדם *Lo middam*, no, it just means that she needs to
not have blood. Of course the question is why would you then
need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to tell me that, of course she
can't have blood, but anyway maybe you would have thought that blood
of you know that maybe blood of לידה leida. *lieda* isn't so
טמא *tamei*, maybe blood of זוב *zov* is even עולה olah, *olah*,
maybe it's completely categorically different. Okay, so that is not a proof.
That says yes she needs שבעה נקיים *shiva nekiyim* but it doesn't
prove whether the status of the days when there's no flow, maybe
it's only referring to the days when there is a flow. ואמר
אביי *Ve-amar Abaye*, מנא אמינא לה *Mena amina lah*, okay I'll try
again. דתניא *Detanya*, we taught in the ברייתא *braisa*. כימי נדתה כך
ימי לידתה *Kimei nidasah kach yimei liedasah*. So there's an analogy right
because the תורה *Torah* says כימי נדת דותה תטמא kimi niddat devotah
titma. *Kimei nidas devosah sitma*, this יולדת yoledes *yoledet* is טמא *tamei*
like a נדה *niddah*, so the נדה *niddah* days are like a
יולדת yoledes *yoledet* days. What's the comparison? מה ימי נדתה אין ראויים
לזיבה *Mah yimei nidasah ein re'uyim le-zivah*, during the seven days during
the period that a woman is a נדה *niddah* from the time
her flow begins she's a נדה *niddah* for seven days, any blood
during that time does not make her a זבה *zavah*. Okay, so
during the נדה *niddah* period she cannot become a זבה *zavah*. Okay,
number one. Number two, ואין ספירת שבעה עולה olah. מהם *ve-ein sefiras
shiva olah mehem*. Number two is let's say when a woman is
a זבה *zavah*, she cannot count her נדה *niddah* days somehow not
count towards her clean days as a זבה *zavah*. Obviously because first
of all it's not even possible, once a woman is a זבה
*zavah* she never becomes a נדה *niddah* again until she stops being
a זבה *zavah*. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s going to say that,
it's really not that it doesn't count but it really is like
אי אפשר *ee efshar*. Okay but basically the point here is נדה
*niddah* and זבה *zavah* are mutually exclusive. When a woman is a
נדה *niddah* she cannot become a זבה *zavah* during those period of
time. When she's a זבה *zavah* she never becomes a נדה *niddah*
until she gets out of being a זבה *zavah* and נדה *niddah*
days don't count towards זבה *zavah* days obviously because they don't even
occur. Okay but the basic point is they're mutually exclusive and now
we're going to say, so because we make the comparison we'll say
the same about יולדת *yoledet* and זבה *zavah* are mutually exclusive. So
you see where this is going. So it says, one minute, אף
ימי לידתה *Af yimei liedasah*, similar to the period of the week
or the two weeks, the period of לידה leida. *lieda*, שאין ראויים
לזיבה *she-ein re'uyim le-zivah*, number one is if she bleeds during that
week or two weeks she does not become a זבה *zavah*, that
makes sense right, it's טומאה tumah *tumah* of לידה *lieda* whatever and
it's like נדה *niddah* she doesn't become a זבה *zavah*. שאין ראויים
לזיבה *She-ein re'uyim le-zivah*. And number two, but the other part is
if she is already a זבה *zavah*, אין ספירת שבעה עולה מהן
*ein sefiras shiva olah mehen*. So the seven so you cannot count
the לידה *lieda* days towards the זבה *zavah* days. So that's the
comparison although it's an אי אפשר מאי אפשר *ee efshar mee-ee efshar*,
the גמרא *Gemara* will say that, but the same way נדה *niddah*
days never count towards זבה *zavah* days why because you never get
נדה *niddah* days when you're a זבה *zavah*. Nevertheless, by comparison, labor
days also never count towards zava days. And this is a proof
like רבא; it's explicit. You can't count those days. ורבא, v'Rava, what
does רבא say to that? הא מני רבי אליעזר היא. Ha meni
Rabbi Eliezer hi. So that's the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer we said
on the עמוד א. amud aleph. We had it on רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer דאמר מפיסה נמי סתרא, de'amar mifisa nami satra, that remember
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that even when something doesn't cause זיבה,
ziva, it can counteract. So therefore, this period which can't cause a
זבה for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, I can say that for him,
you know, it's not necessarily בסותר bisoter but it won't be עולה,
because he doesn't buy into this whole idea of גורם, goreim, only
something that actually causes. But me, that I disagree with רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, and that the only
thing that fully interrupts is גורם, goreim, I'll also say that since
this period is not גורם, goreim, it can even be עולה. So
although it's not exactly רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's similar about what
weight you give things that are not גורם, goreim, and let's just
attribute that to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So אביי actually has a
ברייתא that's explicitly like him, so did רבא, but אביי changed, edited
it. Okay, but here רבא attributes it to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
Now the גמרא wraps this up. וכי דנין אפשר משאי אפשר? Vechi
danin efshar mishai efshar? Can you learn out the possible from the
impossible? Okay, נדה doesn't count towards זבה because it never occurs. That
doesn't mean that יולדת doesn't count from זבה. So אמר רב אחדבוי
בר אמי, Amar Rav Achadvoi bar Ami, רבי אליעזר היא. Rabbi Eliezer
hi. So once we already said רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's another
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer again. What רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? דאמר, de'amar,
it says דאמר דנין אפשר משאי אפשר. de'amar danin efshar mishai efshar.
You're able to do it. So רש"י Rashi points out that it's
in a totally different context about a question about learning out whether
you can use מעשר שני Maaser Sheni for מצה matzah and do
we learn it out from what happened in מצרים Mitzrayim when they
didn't have מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. So anyway, another place where רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, I'm not bothered. Yeah, I can learn out
אפשר משאי אפשר efshar mishai efshar even though it was not even
feasible in the past. Okay. רב ששת אמר, Rav Sheshet amar, על
כרחך היקישן הכתוב. al korchacha hikishan hakatuv. It normally we would say
you can't learn one from the other if it was something arbitrary
like גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. But here when the פסוק pasuk explicitly
equates them, it says כימי נדת דותה תטמא. The תורה is saying
יולדת is like נדה, then it allows us to learn out things
even if it's אפשר משאי אפשר. efshar mishai efshar. ואיכא דאמרי Ve'ika
d'amri some say just that the names were reversed. אמר רב אחדבוי
בר אמי אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Achadvoi bar Ami amar Rav
Sheshet, רבי אליעזר היא—no Rabbi Eliezer hi wait it's the same thing—אמר
רב אחדבוי, Amar Rav Achadvoi, oh no so it's not in the
name of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's in the name of רב
ששת. Rav Sheshet. רבי אליעזר היא Rabbi Eliezer hi דאמר דנין אפשר
משאי אפשר. de'amar danin efshar mishai efshar. ורב פפא אמר, veRav Papa
amar, here's רב פפא Rav Papa who's responding as opposed to before
it was רב ששת Rav Sheshet who was responding, על כרחך היקישן
הכתוב. al korchacha hikishan hakatuv. So again, it's the same point, it's
just it's a difference of who said what. But we didn't conclude
anything. Yeah, correct, we didn't conclude anything. But the basic assumption is
ימי לידה; yimei leida; anyway there's a huge תוספות Tosafot here. If
you want, you can look at the first line of this תוספות,
Tosafot, ל"ז עמוד א, lamed zayin amud aleph, אביי אמר סותרת ואינה
עולה. Abaye amar soteret v'eina olah. כתב אבי בתשובה, Katav Avi bitshuva,
people don't know רש"י Rashi wrote תשובות, teshuvot, he did, we actually
have them collected, אחת, achat, דאביי מודה דימי לידה שאינה רואה בהם
עולים לספירת זיבתה. d'Abaye modeh d'yimei leida she'eina ro'ah bahem olim lisifirat
zivtah. Really the הלכה halacha even אביי admits that it counts. והכי
מוכח בפרק סימן מן הברייתא והכא אליבא דרב מריינוס קאמרינן. Vehachi mochiach
b'perek Siman min habraisa vehacha aliba deRav Marianus kaamrinan. You have only
been talking according to רב מריינוס Rav Marianus but everybody really agrees
להלכה lehalacha that it is עולה לספירת זיבתה. olah lisifirat zivtah. So
did he change his mind somewhere else, is that it? No, he
changed his mind. We're discussing what is the position of רב מריינוס,
Rav Marianus, but his personal position is... Okay, yes. You correctly said
נדה is an איסור כרת. issur kares. Yeah, and זבה and יולדת,
all those things, sex during that period is considered איסור כרת. kares
Because you said something about a man who had sex with a
יולדת becomes טמא. Yes, he's also אסור asur and חייב כרת chayav
kares during that week or two weeks, right. Yeah, but that's not
what we're talking about, but that's correct. It's explicit in the פסוק
pasuk I should say. The only thing explicit in the פסוק is
sex with a נדה, but because the תורה equates the טומאה of
זבה and יולדת to נדה, חז"ל Chazal understand that the כרת applies
in all three cases. Okay, let's get a little further. קשתה שלושה
ימים, Kashta shlosha yamim, back to the major line in the משנה,
Mishna, if a woman has a break of a day from the
pains, then the קושי koshi doesn't matter and she becomes a זבה.
איבעיא להו, Ibeiya lehu, so now we ask the question, שבתה מזה
ומזה מהו? Shavta mizeh umizeh mahu? We said if she has a
break of the pains and she's still bleeding, it interrupts. What if
she has a break of the pains and a break of the
bleeding? Does that interrupt and make it not considered קושי koshi related
to the לידה? Now you could see how you could argue both
ways. You could say that's even a bigger break; all the more
so that it should be unrelated to the לידה. Or you could
say, no, no, if she's bleeding without pains, then it shows that
the bleeding is to some degree not dependent on the pains, and
therefore even when she had the pains before, we, you know, we
sort of bracket the pains because we see there's bleeding even without
pains. But if there's a cessation of both, then the bleeding was
with pains and we'll still say it's based on the לידה. So
that's the question: what is the הלכה if there's a cessation of
both? Does it create a break? Or does it, or no, in
that case actually she can count it? So רב חסדא Rav Chisda
אמר amar טמאה. tmeia. She's טמאה. tmeia. It creates a break the
same way just pains, cessation of just pains creates a break, cessation
of both creates a break. רב חנינא Rav Chanina אמר טהורה. tehora.
No, in that case actually it's fully attributable to the pains and
she's טהורה. tehora. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, so Rabbi Chanina
said, משל למלך שיצא וחיילותיו לפניו. mashal lemelech sheyatza vechayalotav lefanav. So
it's like a king who's going out and he sends his troops
in advance, his advance troops. וידוע שחיילותיו של מלך הן. Veyadua shechayalotav
shel melech hen. You know that they are the troops of the
king. Which means what? Which means that that what I'm sorry that
hold on. Right that the child pains are right right רב חנינא
Rav Chanina is the one that says טהורה. tehora. Right. He says
okay she had pains with with bleeding and then she had nothing.
So but you don't need it to come to the minute before.
The fact that the pains preceded the childbirth means they're related to
the childbirth. So it's not doesn't have to be up to the
last minute. They come before the childbirth they don't have to be
up to the last minute. The only reason that the that the
cessation of pains with the bleeding creates a break is that proves
that the bleeding is not dependent on the pains. So there's not
a הלכה that it has to be right up to the childbirth.
It's just you can't have counter evidence. Bleeding without pains is counter
evidence to the dependency. But if it just came before and then
there was a break big deal. It was something that came in
advance. It was the advance troops. Okay. It doesn't need to happen
right up to the last minute. רב חסדא Rav Chisda אמר, and
Rav Chisda says, כל שכן דבעי נפיש חיילות טפי. kol sheken dba'ei
nafish chayalot tfei. All the more so as the king draws closer
there are even more troops. So it's not you can't just say
the advance troops. If these advance troops if they were all related
to the childbirth it would have continued up to the childbirth. So
it's a nice way of conceptually pointing out and this the debate.
Meaning one idea is it only counts if it leads right up
to the childbirth. So there has to be pains straight up to
the childbirth or else it's not connected. The other thing is no.
The fact that you she's pregnant and you have pains and you
have bleeding means it's based on the childbirth. The only reason that
that's undermined is when there's counter evidence when there's bleeding without pains.
That's the only thing that causes a break. Okay. So let's take
a look. רב חסדא Rav Chisda אמר okay תנן. tnan. Now we
taught in a משנה. mishna. Let's see if we can prove it.
רבי יהושע אומר לילה ויום כלילי שבת ויומו. Rabbi Yehoshua omer layla
veyom kelilei Shabbat veyomo. That what's a break? A full night and
a day, לילה ויום, layla veyom, like the day of שבת, Shabbat,
you know the night and day, a halachic day, not 24 hours.
ששבתה מן הצער ולא מן הדם. Sheshavta min hatza'ar velo min hadam.
And when what creates a break if she breaks from the pain
and not from the blood. So the question is does that mean
only or even? So that's the debate. טעמא דמן הצער ולא מן
הדם. Ta'ama demin hatza'ar velo min hadam. When is it when does
it create an interruption when it's a break from the pain and
not from the blood. הא מזה ומזה טהורה. Ha mizeh umizeh tehora.
If it was a break from both טהורה tehora then it would
it would not cause a break. Then it would be it would
still be related to the childbirth. קשיא דרב חסדא. Kashya deRav Chisda.
It's a contradiction to Rav Chisda who says that that in that
case it is טמאה. tmeia. So אמר לך רב חסדא לא מיבעיא
מזה ומזה דטמאה. Amar lach Rav Chisda lo miba'ya mizeh umizeh detmeia.
No it goes without saying that if both stop that causes a
full break and she's טמאה. tmeia. דפסקו להו חיילות לגמרי. Depasku lehu
chayalot legamrei. Again using that phrase the troops have completely stopped. Meaning
certainly if there's not if it completely breaks that's a break. אבל
מן הצער ולא מן הדם. Aval min hatza'ar velo min hadam. אימא
דעדיין דקא מידמא ולא פסקה. eima de'adayin deka midma velo paska. I
might have thought that if she's still bleeding and it's just that
she's not having pains maybe it's still a continuation of the path
and ואימא כי היכי דמידמא לא פסקה. ve'eima ki heichi demidma lo
paska. The same way she's still bleeding now מכאבי נמי לא פסקה
mik'evi nami lo paska you know what she's also having childbirth pains.
אה ah she says she's not having childbirth pains. בעתויי בעלמא הוא
דנקט לה. ba'atuya be'alma hu denakat lah. Maybe she's you know she's
ill or she's you know she's distracted because of the pregnancy and
she's not aware that she's having these pains but maybe I should
be able to assume that this is also coming with pains. קמ"ל
kamashma lan that it's not. Now some people think that it's a
little bit funny that we should assume that you can have sensations
and not be aware of them but what I always tell people
is okay can stop right now and think can you feel the
weight of your watch on your hand or your glasses on your
hand? And if you stop to think about it you can. But
until I asked you you weren't feeling that weight. So there can
be things that are causing you know stimulating your nerves that you're
not paying attention to and you're not even you know conscious of.
So anyway the גמרא the גמרא here is saying what? We have
the משנה mishna that says what causes the break stopping from pains
not stopping without stopping from blood. And the question is do you
read that only that causes the break but if you stopped from
both there's no break it's connected she's טהורה tehora or do you
read even that causes a break and how much more so if
you stopped both from the pains and from the blood would that
be a complete break and she would be טמאה. tmeia. So that
is the question of how to read the משנה. mishna. Let's see
if we can resolve this. Okay. תנן. tnan. We taught in the
משנה. mishna. קשתה שלושה ימים בתוך אחד עשר יום ושבתה מעת לעת
וילדה הרי זו יולדת בזוב. Kashta shlosha yamim betoch achad asar yom
veshavta me'et le'et veyalda harei zu yoledet bazov. What's the scenario? So
she bleeds for three days with child pains and then she takes
a 24-hour break so then she is a יולדת בזוב yoledet bazov
because of the 24-hour break. So היכי דמי. heichi dami. What's the
case? אילימא כדקתני ilima kedkatani like it says literally they won't. She
had pains and she bled, day two she had pains and she
bled, day three she had pains and she bled, למה לי שלשה
בתרי בקושי וחד בשופי סגי? lamah li shlosha b'trei b'koshi v'chad b'shovi
sagi? It could have had an easier scenario. Why did it have
to give it a scenario of four days, right? Day one pain
bleed, day two pain bleed, day three pain bleed, day four off,
day five childbirth. I can give you the same scenario with three
days. Day one pain bleed, day two pain bleed, day three bleed
no pain, and then childbirth. Okay, because there's no pain on day
three, that creates the break, the 24-hour break, therefore you have three
days of bleeding, they're יולדת בזוב. yoledes b'zov. Why did it have
to give the case with three all three days בקושי? b'koshi? It
could have been two plus one and then childbirth. It didn't need
to be four days, it could have been three days. למה לי
שלש בתרי בקושי וחד בשופי סגי? lamah li shalosh b'trei b'koshi v'chad
b'shovi sagi? אלא לאו הכי קאמר, ela lav hachi ka'amar, this is
what it means. קשתה שלשה, kashtah shlosha, she had קושי koshi for
three days, ושבתה מזה ומזה. v'shavsah mizeh u-mizeh. The reason it gave
you an example of three days and then a day break was
it wanted to give an example of a day break where nothing
happened during that day, no blood, no childbirth. או o or it
would be true the other scenario. קשתה שנים ושבתה מעת לעת, kashtah
shnayim v'shavsah me-eis le-eis, הרי זו יולדת בזוב, harei zu yoledes b'zov,
then that is a יולדת בזוב. yoledes b'zov. ותיובתא דרב חנינא. v'tiuvta
d'rav chanina. Now you have to admit that that is a very
reasonable read of the משנה. mishnah. It says three days bleeding with
קושי, koshi, one day nothing. So the one day nothing means nothing,
no bleeding, no קושי. koshi. If I wanted to say bleeding without
קושי, koshi, I didn't need the fourth day, so it must mean
nothing happened on the fourth day. So the גמרא says ותיובתא דרב
חנינא? v'tiuvta d'rav chanina? אמר לך רב חנינא, amar lach rav chanina,
רב חנינא rav chanina will say back to you: לא, לעולם כדקתני,
lo, l'olam k'dik'tani, it's like it says. והא קא משמע לן, v'ha
ka mashma lan, so why did I need to give the example
of the four days? דאף על גב דמחיל קושי בשלישי, d'af al
gav d'machil koshi b'shlishi, ושבת מעת לעת, v'shavas me-eis le-eis, טמאה. t'mei'ah.
לאפוקי מרב חנינא. l'afokei me'rav chanina. There's a, it's pretty funny, לאפוקי
מרב חנינא, l'afokei me'rav chanina, it's a different רב חנינא, rav chanina,
because he himself is a רב חנינא. rav chanina. But anyway, it's
to tell you, if you remember we had something yesterday which is
you bled for three days, right, if on day three you bled
and then there was 24 hours and then there was childbirth, since
you bled, there was the position of רב חנינא, rav chanina, that
even though there was 24 hours, since you bled the day before
the childbirth, it's always considered connected, even if there's a 24-hour break,
if it was literally the day before. So he says that's why
we had to say one, two, three bleeding and four-day break, because
if it was one, two, three bleeding and the three-day, there was
no קושי, koshi, since it was the day before childbirth, right, then
that would be enough to make it connected and she would be
טהורה, tehorah, and here it's telling you that even with that she
is טמאה. t'mei'ah. Okay, so ברוך השם, baruch hashem, we finished the
דף. daf.